In this exercise on unit tests, we're going to use the built-in Python unit test library
to write test classes and test cases and run our unit tests and make sure that they pass.
So by now you're an expert in Python unit testing, right?
We wrote our first unit test.
We used this exercise to use the unit test library in the standard, in the Python standard
library.
We didn't have to install anything extra, use any other frameworks.
It's all available to us right here.
So let's go to VS Code, I'm going to make a new file, and I'm going to call it divisible.py.
And I'm going to define a new function here, and I'm going to call it divisible.py.
And checking a number, the number that I want to check, and then the divisor.
And I'm going to return, if check number, modulo the divisor is equal to 0.
So if the number that I'm checking is e, and I'm doing a modulo 2, it will be equal
to 0, because 8 is an even number.
Let's make another new file.
This time I'm going to say that as test divisible.py.
And this is where we'll write our unit tests.
So we want to import unit test.
We also want to import the code that we're going to test in a new file.
So I'm going to import, I'm going to say from divisible.
This is the name of our file.
I'm going to import the divisible by method.
I'm going to write a new class, and I'm going to call it divisible test case.
What does it need to inherit from in order to be a valid test case?
Unit test, test case.
That's right.
Unit test.test case.
Now I can go ahead and start writing some tests in here.
Remember the test has to start with test underscore or it's not going to be run.
So I'm going to say test divisible by.
I'm going to pass in itself.
I'm going to use the assert true assertion that if I call divisible by with the arguments of 10 and 2, it should be true.
And if I let's say I want to test that assert true that divisible by for 10 and 3 is also true.
And I'm going to put in a if the name is equal to done domain.
Just run this unit test.
Call the main method on the unit test.
Module here and it knows how to do the rest.
So me is the command palette, run the Python file in my terminal.
And I got an error here.
This assertion error, false is not true.
So this is a good opportunity for me to take a look and say, is it my code that's not correct or is it my test that's not correct.
I got a failure.
Well, it's actually my test that's not correct, right, 10 is not divisible by 3.
So I'm going to change this to false and run the Python file in the ripple again.
Now I should see that one test ran and one test ran and it ran successfully.
I can also run this with the dash reflag or if you pass in two dashes that would be the dash verbose flag.
And that will tell me exactly which test ran and which test case.
The nice thing here is I can have multiple test cases, multiple tests.
And I don't have to do anything special besides for this.
If I didn't have this check for main method here, remember that I could run Python dash, I'm unit test and pass in the name of the module.
So there's no dot pui here. Oops, I'm sorry.
Divisable.
There's no dot pui here where passing in the name of the module, which in this case is the name of the file, ran our test successfully.
Awesome.